<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>mallakhambist.in</title>
    <link href="https://mallakhambist.in/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://mallakhambist.in" />
    <updated>2025-10-06T15:19:26+05:30</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Mallakhambist</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://mallakhambist.in</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Unity in Chennai: All India University Mallakhamb Championship Gets New, Combined Dates!</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mallakhambist</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mallakhambist.in/unity-in-chennai-all-india-university-mallakhamb-championship-gets-new-combined-dates/"/>
        <id>https://mallakhambist.in/unity-in-chennai-all-india-university-mallakhamb-championship-gets-new-combined-dates/</id>
        <media:content url="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/14/Untitled-1.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="Mallakhamb"/>
            <category term="Blog"/>

        <updated>2025-10-03T15:53:06+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/14/Untitled-1.png" alt="" />
                    Both Men's and Women's tournaments will now be held together from October 24-27. Here’s everything you need to know. For weeks, university Mallakhamb teams across India had been marking their calendars and planning their logistics for a split championship. The men were headed to Bilaspur,&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/14/Untitled-1.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <h3><strong>Both Men's and Women's tournaments will now be held together from October 24-27. Here’s everything you need to know.</strong></h3>
<p>For weeks, university Mallakhamb teams across India had been marking their calendars and planning their logistics for a split championship. The men were headed to Bilaspur, Chhattisgarh, while the women were set to showcase their skills in Chennai. Two different cities, two different time slots, creating a divided focus for fans and officials alike.</p>
<p>But in a significant and welcome update that champions unity and celebration, the All India Inter-University (AIU) Mallakhamb Championship for 2025-26 has been consolidated into one grand event!</p>
<p>The fragmented schedule is a thing of the past. Now, the entire Mallakhamb community can turn its collective gaze to one city, as both men and women will compete for national glory under the same roof. This change not only simplifies logistics but promises a more vibrant, festival-like atmosphere for everyone involved.</p>
<hr>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/14/123.jpeg" alt="" width="1075" height="1483" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/14/responsive/123-xs.jpeg 300w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/14/responsive/123-sm.jpeg 480w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/14/responsive/123-md.jpeg 768w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/14/responsive/123-lg.jpeg 1024w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/14/responsive/123-xl.jpeg 1360w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/14/responsive/123-2xl.jpeg 1600w"></figure>
<h3>The Key Details: Mark Your Calendars!</h3>
<p> </p>
<p>All university coaches, managers, and athletes should take immediate note of the revised schedule. The clock is ticking, as the deadline for entries is just around the corner.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Event:</strong> All India Inter-University Mallakhamb Championship 2025-26</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Venue:</strong> <strong>Vinayak Mission Research Foundation, Chennai, Tamil Nadu</strong></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>New Dates:</strong> <strong>October 24th to 27th, 2025</strong></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Participants:</strong> Men &amp; Women (Combined Event)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>IMPORTANT: The last date for submitting entries is October 13th, 2025.</strong></p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Universities are urged to complete their registration formalities before this crucial deadline to ensure their athletes don't miss out on this fantastic opportunity.</p>
<hr>
<p> </p>
<h3>A Convergence of Stars</h3>
<p> </p>
<p>The unified stage in Chennai is set to host a dazzling array of talent, making this one of the most anticipated events on the university sports calendar. All eyes will be on the established stars and rising talents of the Mallakhamb world.</p>
<p>Fans can look forward to seeing powerhouse performers like <strong>Pranav Kori, Kundan Kachhawa, Krishna Ambekar, Praneet Yadav, Rishabh Ghubde</strong> and <strong>Yatin Kori</strong>, among many other gifted athletes from across the country. With the men's and women's events happening simultaneously, the level of competition and excitement is expected to be higher than ever before.</p>
<p>This championship is not just a competition; it's a preview of the future of Mallakhamb.</p>
<hr>
<p> </p>
<h3>A Unified Stage for a United Sport</h3>
<p> </p>
<p>Hosting the men’s and women’s events together is a wonderful step forward, offering equal prominence and celebration for all athletes. It allows for greater camaraderie, shared experiences, and a stronger sense of community.</p>
<p>The countdown has officially begun! With the entry deadline less than two weeks away, the race is on. Get your entries in, book your tickets, and prepare to witness the pinnacle of university Mallakhamb.</p>
<p>Chennai is waiting!</p>
<p>-Mallakhambist</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>SGFI Mallakhamb Nationals: Why Are Two Players Still Being Left on the Sidelines?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mallakhambist</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mallakhambist.in/sgfi-mallakhamb-nationals-why-are-two-players-still-being-left-on-the-sidelines/"/>
        <id>https://mallakhambist.in/sgfi-mallakhamb-nationals-why-are-two-players-still-being-left-on-the-sidelines/</id>
        <media:content url="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/13/SGFI.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="Mallakhamb"/>
            <category term="Blog"/>

        <updated>2025-09-27T12:58:56+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/13/SGFI.png" alt="Why only team of 4 at School Games Federation Of India Nationals and not team of 6 as per actual Mallakhamb rules?" />
                    The air in Ujjain, Madhya Pradesh, will soon be electric with anticipation. From November 24th to 28th, 2025, the nation's most promising young Mallakhamb athletes will converge for the prestigious School Games Federation of India (SGFI) National Championships. They will have spent months, if not&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/13/SGFI.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Why only team of 4 at School Games Federation Of India Nationals and not team of 6 as per actual Mallakhamb rules?" /></p>
                <p> </p>
<h1><strong>A look at the outdated team rules in school-level competition and the opportunities being denied to young athletes.</strong></h1>
<p>The air in Ujjain, Madhya Pradesh, will soon be electric with anticipation. From <strong>November 24th to 28th, 2025</strong>, the nation's most promising young Mallakhamb athletes will converge for the prestigious School Games Federation of India (SGFI) National Championships. They will have spent months, if not years, training for this moment—perfecting their postures, building their strength, and dreaming of a national medal.</p>
<p>But for two members of every single qualifying team, that dream will be cut short before they even get a chance to compete. Why? Because of an outdated rulebook that has failed to keep pace with the rest of the sport.</p>
<hr>
<p> </p>
<h1>A Sport on the Rise: Mallakhamb's Modern Makeover</h1>
<p> </p>
<p>To understand the problem, we first have to look at the incredible progress Mallakhamb has made. The year <strong>2018</strong> marked a turning point. The Mallakhamb Federation of India (MFI) rolled out a new, modernized code of points, bringing significant and much-needed changes to the competition format.</p>
<p>Two of the biggest updates were:</p>
<ol start="1">
<li>
<p><strong>The removal of compulsory sets</strong>, allowing athletes more freedom and creativity in their routines.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>An increase in team size from four to six players</strong>, providing more opportunities and creating deeper, more competitive teams.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The evolution didn't stop there. In <strong>2021</strong>, another progressive change was made to promote all-around skill: female athletes were now required to compete on both <strong>Pole and Rope Mallakhamb</strong>, while male athletes would perform the usual <strong>Pole, Rope, and Hanging Mallakhamb</strong>.</p>
<p>These changes were widely celebrated and quickly adopted by every major Mallakhamb organizing body in the country. From the official Federation tournaments to high-profile events like the Khelo India Youth Games, Khelo India University Games, and the Association of Indian Universities (AIU) championships and the IOC's National Games—the new, modern rules are the standard.</p>
<p>Everywhere, that is, except for one.</p>
<hr>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/13/Madhavsevanyas.png" alt="Madhav Seva Nyas Ujjain" width="1920" height="1280" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/13/responsive/Madhavsevanyas-xs.png 300w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/13/responsive/Madhavsevanyas-sm.png 480w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/13/responsive/Madhavsevanyas-md.png 768w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/13/responsive/Madhavsevanyas-lg.png 1024w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/13/responsive/Madhavsevanyas-xl.png 1360w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/13/responsive/Madhavsevanyas-2xl.png 1600w"><figcaption>Madhav Seva Nyas Ujjain</figcaption></figure>
<p> </p>
<h1>The One Rule SGFI Forgot</h1>
<p> </p>
<p>For reasons that remain unclear, the School Games Federation of India—the very foundation of competitive school sports—is stuck in the past. While they adopted some of the new rules about two years ago (like the removal of compulsory sets and the updated apparatus requirements), they have stubbornly held on to the <strong>outdated four-player team limit</strong>.</p>
<p>This creates a puzzling and frustrating discrepancy. The MFI, the sport's national governing body, has set the standard at six players. Yet, the SGFI, one of its most important grassroots tournaments, operates on a different, archaic system. This isn't just a minor detail; it has a major real-world impact on young athletes.</p>
<hr>
<p> </p>
<h3>More Than Just a Number: The Human Cost of an Outdated Rule</h3>
<p> </p>
<p>Imagine being the fifth or sixth-best player in your state. You train just as hard, make the same sacrifices, and share the same passion as your teammates. You earn your spot through rigorous selection trials. You are, by all measures, one of the top athletes in your region.</p>
<p>Yet, when the time comes to travel to the SGFI Nationals in Ujjain, you are told to stay home. Your opportunity is gone, not because you weren't good enough, but because of a rulebook technicality. This is the reality for countless school-level players. It's a direct injustice that stifles talent and denies deserving athletes the chance to gain invaluable national-level competition experience. It sends a demoralizing message: your hard work doesn't matter as much.</p>
<hr>
<p> </p>
<h1>A Question of Leadership</h1>
<p> </p>
<p>The Mallakhamb Federation of India has undergone two leadership elections since these rules were first updated in 2018. Under two different leadership committees, this critical gap in the SGFI competition model has been allowed to persist. The question must be asked: <strong>Why hasn't the MFI ensured that its own rules are uniformly applied across all major national tournaments?</strong></p>
<p>As the Mallakhamb community looks towards the upcoming SGFI Nationals in Ujjain, the issue is more urgent than ever. Another year will pass, and another cohort of talented athletes will be left watching from the sidelines.</p>
<p>The clock is ticking. When will the SGFI catch up with the times and give every deserving athlete their chance to shine on the national stage?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Write to Mallakhambist to grow our sport.</p>
</blockquote>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Why Athletes Always The Last to Know?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mallakhambist</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mallakhambist.in/why-athletes-always-the-last-to-know/"/>
        <id>https://mallakhambist.in/why-athletes-always-the-last-to-know/</id>
        <media:content url="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/12/Mallakhambist-Banner1.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="Mallakhamb"/>
            <category term="Blog"/>

        <updated>2025-09-02T22:18:58+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/12/Mallakhambist-Banner1.png" alt="Why Athletes Always The Last To Know" />
                    Association of Indian Universities The Annual Sports Calendar for the Association of Indian Universities Games 2025–26 was officially published on 24 May 2025. It had all the details neatly laid out: men’s Mallakhamb at Dr. C.V. Raman University, Bilaspur, Chhattisgarh (25–29 Oct), women’s Mallakhamb at&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/12/Mallakhambist-Banner1.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Why Athletes Always The Last To Know" /></p>
                <figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/12/AIU-Logo.png" alt="Association of Indian Universities " width="600" height="78" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/12/responsive/AIU-Logo-xs.png 300w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/12/responsive/AIU-Logo-sm.png 480w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/12/responsive/AIU-Logo-md.png 768w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/12/responsive/AIU-Logo-lg.png 1024w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/12/responsive/AIU-Logo-xl.png 1360w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/12/responsive/AIU-Logo-2xl.png 1600w"><figcaption>Association of Indian Universities</figcaption></figure>
<p data-start="372" data-end="784"> </p>
<p data-start="372" data-end="784">The Annual Sports Calendar for the <strong data-start="407" data-end="445">Association of Indian Universities Games 2025–26</strong> was officially published on <strong data-start="474" data-end="489">24 May 2025</strong>. It had all the details neatly laid out: <strong data-start="568" data-end="588">men’s Mallakhamb</strong> at <em data-start="592" data-end="641">Dr. C.V. Raman University, Bilaspur, Chhattisgarh (25–29 Oct)</em>, <strong data-start="643" data-end="665">women’s Mallakhamb</strong> at <em data-start="669" data-end="727">Vinayak Mission Research Foundation, Chennai (20–24 Oct)</em>, and a <strong data-start="735" data-end="781">last date for entries of 22 September 2025</strong>.</p>
<p data-start="786" data-end="881">On paper, this looks perfectly planned. In reality? Most athletes only found out <em data-start="867" data-end="878">last week</em>.</p>
<p data-start="883" data-end="1185">Yes, you read that right. A tournament announced three months ago was a secret for many until just a few days back. Meanwhile, some universities had already held trials, formed squads, and even started training camps weeks ago. Others? Still scrambling to decide <em data-start="1146" data-end="1152">when</em> to hold selections, if at all.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/12/Screenshot-2025-09-02-at-10.28.57-PM.png" alt="AIU Sports Calendar for Indigenous Sports" width="879" height="750" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/12/responsive/Screenshot-2025-09-02-at-10.28.57-PM-xs.png 300w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/12/responsive/Screenshot-2025-09-02-at-10.28.57-PM-sm.png 480w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/12/responsive/Screenshot-2025-09-02-at-10.28.57-PM-md.png 768w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/12/responsive/Screenshot-2025-09-02-at-10.28.57-PM-lg.png 1024w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/12/responsive/Screenshot-2025-09-02-at-10.28.57-PM-xl.png 1360w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/12/responsive/Screenshot-2025-09-02-at-10.28.57-PM-2xl.png 1600w"><figcaption>AIU's Sports Calendar 2025-26 for Indigenous Sports.</figcaption></figure>
<p data-start="1187" data-end="1215"> </p>
<p data-start="1187" data-end="1215">So, the obvious questions:</p>
<ul data-start="1217" data-end="1509">
<li data-start="1217" data-end="1302">
<p data-start="1219" data-end="1302"><strong data-start="1219" data-end="1300">Why wasn’t the calendar made public for athletes the minute it was published?</strong></p>
</li>
<li data-start="1303" data-end="1407">
<p data-start="1305" data-end="1407"><strong data-start="1305" data-end="1405">How did some universities know so early, while others stayed clueless? Insider advantage, maybe?</strong></p>
</li>
<li data-start="1408" data-end="1509">
<p data-start="1410" data-end="1509"><strong data-start="1410" data-end="1507">And why are athletes—the very people these tournaments are meant for—always the last to know?</strong></p>
</li>
</ul>
<h1 data-start="1511" data-end="1531">Unequal Starts</h1>
<p data-start="1532" data-end="1871">For sports like Mallakhamb, preparation isn’t just about turning up with a team. It takes months of conditioning, refining techniques, and getting used to specialized apparatus. When some athletes get weeks of structured training camps and others barely get time to recover from their selection trials, how is this a level playing field?</p>
<p data-start="1873" data-end="2147">Imagine being a student who hears about the competition only a couple of weeks before entries close. You juggle academics, exams, maybe even part-time work—and now you’re expected to be competition-ready against athletes who’ve had head start prep time. Fair? Not even close.</p>
<h1 data-start="2149" data-end="2173">The Larger Problem</h1>
<p data-start="2174" data-end="2440">This isn’t a one-off hiccup. It’s a pattern. Every year, the calendar gets finalized in neat PDFs and official circulars. But somewhere between the AIU’s announcement and the athletes who actually step onto the field, the message gets lost—or deliberately delayed.</p>
<p data-start="2442" data-end="2737">Why? Bureaucratic lag? Universities not bothering to circulate the information? Or is it that some universities, with better connections, always seem to get the memo early? Whatever the reason, the outcome is the same: <strong data-start="2661" data-end="2735">the system rewards a few, while leaving the majority to play catch-up.</strong></p>
<h1 data-start="2739" data-end="2760">Fixing the Game</h1>
<p data-start="2761" data-end="3020">It doesn’t have to be this way. Imagine if, the moment the GR is released, the schedule is posted on an official, athlete-facing platform—social media, a central website, even WhatsApp groups run by federations. No middlemen, no selective leaks, no excuses.</p>
<p data-start="3022" data-end="3251">And why not make trial deadlines uniform across universities? That way, no team has a head start, and every athlete gets a fair chance. After all, the goal of university sport isn’t just to host events—it’s to <em data-start="3232" data-end="3248">develop talent</em>.</p>
<h1 data-start="3253" data-end="3272">Final Whistle</h1>
<p data-start="3273" data-end="3554">The Mallakhamb events of 2025 are a reminder of how broken the communication system in university sports really is. Athletes shouldn’t have to rely on whispers, late emails, or sheer luck to know when their big tournaments are happening. They deserve clarity, time, and fairness.</p>
<p data-start="3556" data-end="3735">Until that happens, the Association of Indian Universities Games will remain less about sporting excellence and more about who knew what, when. And that’s not a game anyone signed up to play.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title> The Legendary Origins of Mallakhamb: The Ancient Indian Sport of Strength and Art</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mallakhambist</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mallakhambist.in/origins-of-mallakhamb/"/>
        <id>https://mallakhambist.in/origins-of-mallakhamb/</id>
        <media:content url="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/11/Origins-of-Mallakhamb-Recovered.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="Mallakhamb"/>
            <category term="Blog"/>

        <updated>2025-08-14T13:57:53+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/11/Origins-of-Mallakhamb-Recovered.png" alt="The Legendary Origin of Mallakhamb" />
                    India is a land that breathes culture and tradition. From spices that changed global trade routes, to yoga that heals millions, to cinema and cricket that capture imaginations—its gifts to the world are endless. But hidden among these treasures lies something extraordinary. A sport both&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/11/Origins-of-Mallakhamb-Recovered.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="The Legendary Origin of Mallakhamb" /></p>
                <p data-start="437" data-end="650">India is a land that breathes culture and tradition. From spices that changed global trade routes, to yoga that heals millions, to cinema and cricket that capture imaginations—its gifts to the world are endless.</p>
<p data-start="652" data-end="836">But hidden among these treasures lies something extraordinary. A sport both fierce and graceful. A sport where the human body becomes poetry in motion. A sport called <strong data-start="819" data-end="833">Mallakhamb</strong>.</p>
<p data-start="838" data-end="1094">If you’ve ever seen an athlete spin around a pole, hanging upside down with impossible balance, or glide through the air on a rope as if gravity didn’t exist—you’ve witnessed Mallakhamb. It’s a spectacle that’s equal parts <strong data-start="1061" data-end="1091">athletic feat and art form</strong>.</p>
<p data-start="1096" data-end="1177">But the story of Mallakhamb isn’t just about training. It begins with a legend.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/11/123-2.avif" alt="Mallakhamb in front of Red Fort, Delhi, India." width="700" height="394">
<figcaption >Image courtesy - blackbeltmag.com</figcaption>
</figure>
<p data-start="1096" data-end="1177"> </p>
<h1 data-start="1184" data-end="1225">The Challenge No One Dared to Accept</h1>
<p data-start="1227" data-end="1506">The year was the late 1700s. The Nizam of Hyderabad was proud of two men in his court: Ali and Gulab—giants of wrestlers, said to be nearly eight feet tall, their muscles carved like stone. They were undefeated. No one in India—or the world—had ever managed to throw them down.</p>
<p data-start="1508" data-end="1610">When they arrived at the court of <strong data-start="1542" data-end="1563">Peshwa Bajirao II</strong> in Pune, they issued a thunderous challenge:</p>
<p data-start="1612" data-end="1673">“Bring us your best wrestler. Let him face us—if he dares.”</p>
<p data-start="1675" data-end="1849">The royal court fell silent. <strong data-start="1704" data-end="1727">Fifty-two wrestlers</strong> stood frozen, none willing to risk their life and honor. The Peshwa’s pride was at stake, and defeat seemed inevitable.</p>
<figure ><figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/11/balambhattadada.jpg" alt="Balambhatta Dada Deodhar: The Father of Mallakhamb" width="647" height="778" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/11/responsive/balambhattadada-xs.jpg 300w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/11/responsive/balambhattadada-sm.jpg 480w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/11/responsive/balambhattadada-md.jpg 768w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/11/responsive/balambhattadada-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/11/responsive/balambhattadada-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/11/responsive/balambhattadada-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<figcaption >Balambhatta Dada Deodhar: The Father of Mallakhamb</figcaption>
</figure>
<p data-start="1675" data-end="1849"> </p>
<p data-start="1851" data-end="1990">That’s when one man stepped forward. Not a hulking wrestler, but a teacher. The court’s physical instructor—<strong data-start="1959" data-end="1988">Balambhatta Dada Deodhar.</strong></p>
<h1 data-start="1997" data-end="2035">The Dream That Changed Everything</h1>
<p data-start="2037" data-end="2164">Balambhatta Dada asked for time. He returned to his hometown of <strong data-start="2096" data-end="2118">Kothure, in Nashik</strong>, carrying the burden of his people’s honor.</p>
<p data-start="2166" data-end="2301">Day after day, he trained. He prayed to his ancestral goddess, <strong data-start="2229" data-end="2245">Saptashrungi</strong>, for strength. And then—one night—everything changed.</p>
<p data-start="2303" data-end="2430">The goddess appeared in his dream and whispered:<br data-start="2351" data-end="2354">“Worship Lord Hanuman, the god of power. Only then will victory be yours.”</p>
<p data-start="2432" data-end="2648">That very night, Lord Hanuman himself came to Balambhatta—in the form of a monkey. On a wooden pole, the divine monkey performed dazzling acrobatics, twisting, leaping, and balancing in ways no human could imagine.</p>
<p data-start="2650" data-end="2724">When Balambhatta Dada awoke, his heart was racing. He knew what he had to do.</p>
<p data-start="2726" data-end="2944">He built the same wooden pole from his dream. He trained on it day and night, mastering movements inspired by Hanuman’s divine performance. What began as prayer became power. What began as desperation became destiny.</p>
<h1 data-start="2951" data-end="2976">The Day of Reckoning</h1>
<p data-start="2978" data-end="3124">The court was overflowing with spectators on the day of the fight. Whispers ran through the crowd: <em data-start="3077" data-end="3122">Could this teacher really fight the giants?</em></p>
<p data-start="3126" data-end="3252">Ali stepped forward first. He smirked at the smaller man before him. But within moments, his confidence turned to confusion.</p>
<p data-start="3254" data-end="3488">Balambhatta Dada moved unlike any wrestler Ali had ever seen—his techniques drawn from the pole, swift and fluid, almost otherworldly. Then, in a flash, Balambhatta Dada locked Ali’s neck between his legs, spun, and slammed him to the ground.</p>
<p data-start="3490" data-end="3541">Ali—the undefeated titan—was defeated in minutes.</p>
<p data-start="3543" data-end="3597">The crowd erupted. The impossible had just happened.</p>
<p data-start="3599" data-end="3721">Seeing his partner’s downfall, Gulab panicked. Instead of stepping forward, he fled. The match was over before it began.</p>
<p data-start="3723" data-end="3828">The Peshwas cheered. The teacher had saved their honor. From that day on, he was honored as <strong data-start="3815" data-end="3826">“Dada.”</strong></p>
<h1 data-start="3835" data-end="3863">The Birth of Mallakhamb</h1>
<p data-start="3865" data-end="4128">The wooden pole Balambhatta Dada had built became more than a training tool. It was a bridge between worship and warfare, between art and athletics. Wrestlers—<em data-start="4019" data-end="4027">mallas</em>—began to train on it, and soon, the practice earned its name: <strong data-start="4090" data-end="4126">Mallakhamb, the wrestler’s pole.</strong></p>
<p data-start="4130" data-end="4378">What started as a weapon of survival grew into a tradition. And today, centuries later, it has evolved into a <strong data-start="4240" data-end="4276">modern sport practiced worldwide</strong>—a breathtaking blend of strength, flexibility, and artistry, standing proudly alongside gymnastics.</p>
<h1 data-start="4385" data-end="4407">More Than a Sport</h1>
<figure class="post__image" ><figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://mallakhambist.in/media/posts/11/mallah.gif" alt="Old Mallakhamb Pyramid picture" width="600" height="936"></figure>
<figcaption >Image courtesy - sports.indiapress.org</figcaption>
</figure>
<p> </p>
<p data-start="4409" data-end="4538">Mallakhamb is not just exercise. It’s a story of resilience. A reminder that when tradition meets creativity, legends are born.</p>
<p data-start="4540" data-end="4790">The pole that once saved a kingdom’s honor now inspires athletes across the globe. And as the sport continues to grow, it carries with it the spirit of its origins—<strong data-start="4704" data-end="4788">the courage of Balambhatta Dada, the blessing of Hanuman, and the soul of India.</strong></p>
<p data-start="4797" data-end="4926"> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
